你这是要我们走向死亡
You would have us march to our end?
我这是要大家得到自由
I would have us free.
不管有没有你
With or without you
我都要向罗马进军
I shall march upon Rome.
你是马科斯•克拉苏的奴隶
You were slave to Marcus Crassus himself?
以前是
I was.
为什么她还是不顾一切地离开我
Why would she risk all to fly from loving arms?
明天我们跟克雷斯同去罗马
Tomorrow we move for rome with Crixus.
但我要你和斯巴达克斯一起走
Yet I would have you take with Spartacus.
我要永远在你身边
My place is forever with you.
这次不行
Not in this.
那个妓女坎莎拉说她看到你从克芮帐篷里出来
The whore Canthara tells of how she saw you come from Kore's tent.
别装了 小子
Game is over boy.
跟娘们一样被爆菊
Take it like a woman.
罗马 终于近在咫尺了
Rome at last lies within our grasp!
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《血祭亡魂》
咱们这些人就吃一只兔子
One fucking hare between us?
小声点
Lower voice.
我可不像个孩子似的 还怕黑
I do not tremble in the dark as frightened child.
火把拿到面前
Carry torch forward!
下次换你拿弓箭
Time next, you carry bow.
老娘都没时间玩了
Too far from fucking blood.
取走他们的武器和盔甲
Strip them of weapons and armor.
还有他们带的粮草
and what supplies they yet carry.
他们是从北方来的
These men travel from the north.
克拉苏派他们来这儿干什么
What purpose would Crassus have there?
他手下的人都有公牛的徽记
Those who follow him are known by mark of the bull.
他们不是克拉苏的手下
These are not his men.
雄鹰和海豚
The eagle and the dolphin.
我见过这样的标志
I have laid eyes upon crest before.
是格涅乌斯•庞培•麦格勒斯的
The mark of Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus.
庞培
Pompey?
他水战陆战都精通
A master of both land and sea.
我丈夫对他敬仰已久
My husband spoke with deep admiration of the man.
常说他是罗马最伟大的战士
Bending tongue to welcome him as Rome's greatest warrior
我听说过他的本事
I have heard tale of his conquests.
也知道他少年屠夫的大名
And name of Adolescent Butcher given him.
我们屠了他的鸟和鱼
We shall butcher bird and fish!
我以为庞培正忙于对战塞多留的叛军
I thought Pompey mired in Hispania against the renegade Sertorius.
正因为他不在 才由克拉苏率军与我们交战
His absence the reason Crassus took arms against us.
既然庞培的探子回了共和国
If Pompey's scouts return to the Republic,
不出一天
as night follows day,
他就会带领人马尾随而来
the man and his legions will trail their shadow.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
有个骑马的过来了
A rider approaches.
说不定是声东击西
This may hold but distraction!
两翼有动静就报个信
Give voice if eyes fall upon movement upon flanks!
他穿着罗马军队的斗篷
They wear cloak of the fucking legion.
那不是罗马人
That is no Roman.
喝点吧
Drink.
没必要浪费在死人身上
Do not waste such on the dead.
你还活着
You yet live.
我不过是个影子
I a but pale shade,
游荡在空虚的世间罢了
haunting a world fallen from meaning.
那我们也要照看好你的魂灵
Then we must nourish specter,
让你重获生命
so that it may reclaim flesh
迎接美好的未来
and promise of better days.
我眼中看不到未来
There stand none upon horizon.
他是如他梦想的那样
Was his end as he had always dreamed?
在战场上光荣战死吗
In glorious battle?
是战场没错
In battle, yes.
却毫无光荣可言
Though robbed of glory.
说出来
Tell of it.
也许你心里会好受一些
That we may share in the burden of grief.
我们跟你分开后 一路获胜
The days after we parted were filled with victory.
敌人的鲜血染红了大地
The blood of our enemies turning fields to crimson mud,
尸首枕藉
thick with the dead.
罗马近在咫尺
Rome lay within our grasp.
胜利却被克拉苏和他的军队夺走
Only to have it snatched from us by Crassus and his legions.
是他亲手
It was the man himself
杀了克雷斯
that robbed Crixus' life?
克雷斯
Crixus!
克雷斯和叛徒恺撒交手
Crixus was engaged by the traitor Caesar.
那个乳臭未干的小子
When boy of scant years
一矛从背后戳穿了他
pierced back with spear.
操蛋的兔崽子
A fucking boy.
艾力冈呢
What of Agron?
他与克雷斯共赴黄泉了吗
Does he share fate with Crixus?
还是依然活在世上
Or is he yet of this world?
克拉苏放我一条生路 就是为了
There is but single reason crassus spare my life.
嘲讽斯巴达克斯只能有如此下场
To taunt Spartacus with vision of his end.
克拉苏想刺激你做出傻事
Crassus tempts to goad you into foolish action.
若不是要为其他人的生命负责
If I stood only for my own life,
也许我会那么冲动
perhaps I would stand so moved.
但我们不能那样做
Yet we must turn from such thoughts,
要考虑迫在眉睫的问题
and set purpose towards more pressing concern.
庞培
Pompey.
他派兵南去 找克拉苏的军队
His scouts were headed south, towards Crassus' legions.
如果信使不回去 他还会派出更多
He will send more, when they do not return.
他们合二为一 两面夹击 我们难以抵挡
We cannot afford to be caught between two armies, fighting as one.
的确不行
No. We cannot.
高卢人的手下没一个开口的吗
None among the Gaul's men form words of note?
为了让他们开口 我们用了鞭刑和烙刑
We have set lash and heated iron towards the loosening of tongues.
我会不断施压 直到有人松口
I shall press until one unmoors from stubborn tether.
不然就把他们的舌头统统拔了
Or command all torn from rebellious root.
我没时间也没精力为这种事分心
I have time nor patience to pause for such distraction.
传令下去 太阳东升之时
Give word to break encampment
我们就启程
as Apollo approaches eastern sky.
我们要加快脚步
I would quicken pace.
随从营地里发生了一件小事
There is a matter of some small concern within the followers' camp.
有个叫坎莎拉的妓女
A whore by the name of Canthara,
遭人毒打 从下体到喉咙都被割开了
discovered beaten and slit as pig from womanhood to throat.
坎莎拉 你知道这件事吗 恺撒
Canthara? What do you know of this, Caesar?
完全不知道
News only now falls upon ear.
我找这个女人好几天了
I have been seeking the woman for several days.
无论她惹了谁 这人的报复心可不容小觑
Whoever she angered, his wrath is a thing to be feared.
随从营地离我军很近
Followers' camp is but brief step from our very ranks.
决不容许出现骚乱和谋杀
I would not have it fall to chaos and murder.
我会亲自处理这件事
I shall personally attend to matter.
希望凶手血债血偿
May those responsible suffer equal fate.
报告
Imperator.
有两名士兵骑马前来
Two soldiers approach on horseback,
佩戴庞培的徽章
bearing crest of Pompey.
屠夫终于露脸了
The butcher at last reveals himself.
把他们带到我的大帐里
See them to my praetorium.
格涅乌斯•庞培•麦格勒斯总督
Proconsul Gnaeu Pompeius Magnus…
愿与您携手剿灭叛贼斯巴达克斯
offers support in campaign against the rebel Spartacus.
这话可真是出乎意料
Offer greeted with wondrous surprise.
若非关乎自身利益 庞培从未协助过任何人
I've never known Pompey to support any cause but his own interests.
抱歉
Apologies.
我只负责传信
I but carry message.
还有什么要说的
Hmmm, see remainder fall from tongue.
庞培要求会面
Pompey requests meeting.
如果要见面 他为何不亲自前来
Why does he not appear before us himself, if taken by such desire?
因为他不是傻子
Because he does not stand the fool.
对吧
Does he?
我不会冒险前往你们的营地
I will not risk journey to your commander's camp.
也不会放弃指挥权
Nor will I break from my charge
对那个自以为是的家伙卑躬屈膝
to bow and scrap before imagined titan.
庞培想在两军之间会面
Pompey seeks but neutral ground.
他带二十个随从 您也一样
Twenty men attending him, to be met in kind.
我要考虑一下
I will consider terms.
给他们吃的喝的
See them to food and wine.
告退
Imperator.
您不是真的考虑跟他会面吧
You cannot seriously be turning offer upon mind?
庞培只是想利用您对斯巴达克斯的了解
Pompey but seeks your knowledge of Spartacus
窃取我们的胜利果实
so that he may snatch victory from deserving hands.
恺撒 你同意我的说法吧
Caesar, you agree, do you not?
我也有和你一样的顾虑
I share your concerns.
但庞培打败塞多留后荣耀加身
Yet Pompey returns the hero against Sertorius,
携英雄之名归来
ripe with laurels.
拒绝他的协助 也许他视其为侮辱
To refuse offer would be considered insult.
到时候他在元老院中以此对你不利
One that could be set against you within the Senate.
去他妈的元老院
To shit with the Senate.
跟他联手还有一个实际的好处
There is practical reason as well to accept terms.
我们可以从南边进攻
We could press attack from the south,
而庞培可以阻止
Pompey could stay Spartacus
斯巴达克斯遁入山中逃跑
from gaining the mountains and slipping from grasp.
一网打尽
With all who follow him.
我决不能放他们逃走
A thing I would not see come to pass.
父亲 您不能去
Father, you cannot go.
这样一来 庞培成了发号施令的人
It would appear Pompey commands you.
这一点我也考虑过了
Again, I share concern.
你不能给他低人一等的印象
You should give no impression that you are beneath him.
派个有头有脸的人物代你去谈判即可
Instead send honored name in your place to broach negotiation.
我猜你说的那位人物就是恺撒吧
And I suppose such name holds letters forming "Caesar"?
不 只有代统帅行使权力的人才
No. Only the imperator's word
有这个资格
and will holds such lofty position.
庞培是个精明的对手
Pompey stands shrewd opponent.
我希望找个经验更丰富的人来对付他
I would have one of more seasoned years to set against him.
提比略提出过良策 证明了他的能力
Tiberius has proven himself worthy advisory.
看他年纪轻轻 庞培自然也会掉以轻心
His youth will but cause Pompey to lower his guard,
最终要他后悔莫及
to deepest regret.
恺撒终于说了几句我爱听的话
Caesar at last breaks words that I am moved to embrace.
我们在你回来前暂且按兵不动
We shall pause advance until your return.
搞清庞培的真实意图 但不要涉及关键问题
Weigh Pompey's true intent yet give upon no issue.
我代表父亲 必定不辱您的威名
I shall stand as my father, unforgiving in command.
转变可以如此之快吗
Was it so short a span,
不久前他还是个迷茫的孩子
when he stood uncertain boy?
那些日子已经随风而去了
Such days have faded from memory.
他现在是个顶天立地的男人
He stands a man now.
我希望他得到应得的一切
And I wish for him all that he deserves.
你没注意防守
You lower the fucking guard.
你要拿我当罗马人 拿命来拼
Do so against the Roman, fought your ass!
纳西尔
Nasir.
这是新兵
Point new army.
记住我给你上的这堂课
Take me upon a lesson.
走吧 我们吃点东西去
Come, let's feel so content as well
我没兴趣
I have no desire.
说两句也不愿意吗
No larish words?
你要打起精神 兴许有好消息
You have taken nonsense and fortunate news.
还真能说
You bold say.
可惜你跟他根本就不是一路人
Does not lift spirit now in the man sill between you and your heart
这话说出来毫无作用
forever removed from path.
我跟艾力冈有过节
I often disagreement with Agron,
但不代表我不关心他的命运
yet I am not absent feeling towards his fate.
以及为他伤心的人
Or wounded upon the one he deserving.
你这是要乘虚而入吗
You take it fucking opportunity?
我只是想给你信心
I seek only to give confidence.
你还有这样的心思
You seek what you always have.
艾力冈就因为这个才走的
Agron has gone because of it.
他不在了
He is gone.
是因为他自己做的决定
because he made choice.
他是因为我才死的
He is gone because of me.
若非他发现我看你的眼神
He would not leave with Crixus
他就不会跟克雷斯走
if he did not see the way my eyes fell upon you!
我们的生活够苦了
The only thing the time we live
但愿诸神不要再折磨我们
and the gods turn away the suffering.
你曾是马科斯•克拉苏的奴隶吗
You were slave to Marcus Crassus?
在米利亚峰从他营中逃脱的吗
The one that slipped from him upon Melia Ridge?
我听说过传言
I have heard rumor.
说他曾宠幸过你
That he was of a favor towards you.
确实有过这样一段日子
There stood such a time.
那你一定跟他很亲近吧
Then you were of a closeness to him.
在你逃跑之前
Before you fled.
我那晚在他的帐篷中
I shared his tent that night.
我拿着刀
I took knife and
趁他睡着悄悄溜走了
slipped from presence while he slept.
你为什么没有趁机下手
Why did you not seize opportunity?
结束他的性命
And end his life?
如果克拉苏那晚死了
If Crassus had fallen that night,
那克雷斯就不会离开人世了
then Crixus would yet be of this world.
我为你失去爱人深感痛心
I am moved by your loss.
但我不该为此负责
Yet I cannot be held for it.
我们都该为自己的行为负责
We are all held for our actions.
我们做出的选择
The choices we make.
我们所做的事
The things that we do.
我们本该做却没有做的事
And those that we should have.
我们无法让太阳西升东落
We cannot reverse the sun.
也无法让时光倒流
Nor relive days past.
是不能
No.
我们只能准备迎接不确定的未来
We can but brace against uncertain future.
等时机一到
And when moment presents,
让那些伤心欲绝的人得到安慰
balance scale against those who have most deeply wounded heart.
通知庞培我到了
Inform Pompey of my arrival.
守在我旁边
Stay at my side.
如果他敢稍有动作 就拔剑
If the man makes but slightest move, unleash sword.
让我们和你的将军说话
Let us break words with your commander.
听听他有什么要说的
And divine his intent.
他非常热切地盼望见到您
He stands most eager to greet you.
尊敬的庞培
Honored Pompey.
家父深表遗憾 他不能…
My father sends regret that he could not
感到遗憾是我
The regret is mine.
我原以为会见到统帅本人呢
I had hoped to embrace the Imperator himself.
结果送上门的只是克拉苏的小崽子而已
Yet fate delivers mere shadow of the name Crassus.
就是这把剑
Is this the blade?
夺走了克雷斯的性命吧
The one that robbed Crixus of his life?
把这小子的手下都绑起来带走
See the boy's men bound and readied for march.
起来
Get up!
你要留他们的性命吗
You would keep them alive?
我要用他们来向死者献祭
I would see them give honor to the dead.
然后再要他们的狗命
In advance of joining their ranks.
你不必拿刀
You will have no need of that.
我跟坎莎拉的死无关
I had no hand in Canthara's fate.
那个让她凄惨离世的人
The one who commanded her so rudely from this world
再也不能作恶了
will never again cause harm.
你知道害她性命的禽兽是谁吗
You know the animal that took her life?
一只乳臭未干的羔羊 自以为是恶狼
A bleating sheep who mistook himself as fearsome wolf.
他已经中计 必死无疑
Maneuvered towards deserved slaughter.
我愿不惜一切 看他受苦受难
I would give all to lay eyes upon his suffering.
我们为他的死来庆祝一下吧
Let us take comfort in thoughts of blood.
肉体的温暖 活人的欢愉
And the warmth of flesh, yet among the living…
怎么抓到的不是克拉苏
What of Crassus?
引他上钩的计划出了点意外
Plan to lure him to his doom falls short of mark.
住手
Stay your hand!
我不希望这小子和他的人轻易就死了
I would not have the boy and his men fall to errant wrath!
他们的血还有更大的用途
Their blood is to serve higher purpose!
角斗
Games?
祭奠死者
To honor the fallen.
宽慰那些还活着的人
And give comfort to those left in death's wake.
我见过这把剑
I have seen this before.
在克雷斯的手中
In Crixus' hands.
那小崽子在战场上拿这把剑…
And the boy's upon field of battle as it…
他的名字叫提比略
His name is Tiberius.
是马科斯•克拉苏的儿子
He is the son of Marcus Crassus.
他现在正与他的一帮士兵关在一起
He stands prisoner with a clutch of his soldiers.
我要把他千刀万剐
I will have his fucking life.
所以我们暂且留着他的小命
The reason he yet clings to it.
让我们搭起柴堆
Let us build pyre
聚拢在假想中的传奇竞技场上
and gather around imagined sands of storied arena.
庄重地看那沙场上刀剑相交
To bear solemn witness to the clash of sword and shield.
向高卢战神致以最后的敬意
And pay final tribute to the Undefeated Gaul.
他的英勇将永存我心
Who shall forever stand so in my eyes.
不久之前
There was a time not along ago
他质疑你的权威
when he turned from you.
这些都是我怂恿的
A thing I moved him towards.
过去的事常常不能如愿
The past is seldom as we would have it.
但未来在我们手中
The future yet to be known.
拥抱当下
Embrace the present,
别的什么都不要想了
and strike all else from concern.
那便来一场角斗吧
Let us have your games.
每一滴溅出的罗马人的鲜血
Each drop of Roman blood spilled
都在向那些逝去的人致意
in honor of those who have been taken from us.
死吧 罗马狗
Die Roman dog!
我认识这一个
I know this one.
来自莱茵河东岸的艾力冈
Agron. From the lands east of the Rhine.
野蛮民族 他们连自己人都不信任
A savage people, holding no trust even among their own kind.
这一个有些不同
This one is of a difference.
他是斯巴达克斯身边的要人
A gladiator standing beside Spartacus in valued position,
就连凯尔特人甘尼克斯和阵亡的高卢人
the Celt Gannicus and the fallen Gaul
也不过跟他平起平坐
his only equals.
他开口没有
Has he given voice?
骂声不断 统帅
Only to rude curse, Imperator.
我还没骂完呢
There is yet more upon tongue,
你们这些该死的贱人
you fucking cunts…
都半死不活了
More dead than living,
还骂得这么起劲
yet still conjures breath toward insult.
我很想拥有这样的角斗士
I would care to own gladiators such as this,
好好磨砺一番这个顽固的家伙
and turn hard men toward harder purpose.
我倒是想看顽石点头
As I would see this one softened.
将他钉在十字架上
Nail him to cross…
给那些不肯乖乖开口的人一个警示
stand warning to all who refuse to break proper word.
我他妈迟早要将你的头砍下来
I shall yet… have your fucking head.
想法不错
An impressive feat,
只可惜你再也不能用剑了
For one who will never again grasp sword…
要是跟随斯巴达克斯的人都有这种下场就好了
Would that all who follow Spartacus shared like fate.
统帅
Imperator.
庞培的使者到了
An envoy from Pompey has arrived.
提比略呢
What of Tiberius?
他并未和他们一道前来
He does not stand among them.
克拉苏统帅
Imperator Crassus.
我从庞培总督那里带来口信
I carry message from Proconsul Pompeius
我的儿子呢
Where is my son?
您的儿子
Your son…?
和你们的两个信使一道
Dispatched with two of your reflection
找你们的将军谈话去了
to break word with your commander.
抱歉 我对您的儿子一无所知
Apologies, I know nothing of your son,
派到您这儿来的只有我
nor others sent to you in my place.
我是唯一的信使
I am sole envoy
当时他们身上戴有庞培的徽章
They stood before me bearing fucking mark of Pompey!
有其他信使派出来
Other messengers were dispatched.
但不是到您这里的
Yet not to you.
有没有信使未返回营地的
Have any failed to report?
有一队往拉丁姆去的信使下落不明
A clutch of men, heading south towards Latium.
下去吧
Leave us.
他们是斯巴达克斯的人
They were Spartacus' men,
装扮成庞培士兵的样子
posing as Pompey's.
你不可能知道的…
You can not know this
可你该知道 你在希留爱沙的叛贼当中待过
You do should have! You stood among the rebels in Sinuessa!
城里有数以千计的人
There were thousands within the city.
我要是能认出那家伙是谁
Fortune would be most kind for me to know
简直是撞了大运
the one that presented himself.
诸神把我们害惨了
The gods rain shit upon us.
亏得诸神保佑
Yet is it not blessing,
没让你掉进叛贼所设的陷阱
that they stayed you from being ensnared in clever plot?
要是统帅你死于斯巴达克斯之手
If the Imperator were to fall to Spartacus
提比略现在生死未卜 不要乱说
We do not know that Tiberius has fallen.
他是克拉苏家族的一员
He carries the name of Crassus.
我愿意拿世上所有的财物换他一命
And with him the worth of the world towards bargain.
你相信他还活着
You believe him alive?
和任何父亲一样
As any father would,
活要见人 死要见尸
absent eyes laid upon lifeless form.
那么我们祈祷事情有好的结果吧
Then we must pray towards proper outcome,
等待斯巴达克斯把你儿子…
and wait for Spartacus to return
我不会在我儿子命悬一线之时
I will not stand idle while my son's life
还无所作为
dangles by fraying thread.
我们知道斯巴达克斯的行军方向
We know which direction Spartacus heads
一小队人快马加鞭就可以赶上他并与其谈判
A few men fleet upon horse could overtake him and broach trade.
斯巴达克斯一看到你就会动手
Spartacus will kill you upon sight,
不计代价
regardless of cost.
我派鲁弗斯去执行任务
I shall set Rufus towards task.
我倒是认为某个
I would place trust in someone
更熟悉斯巴达克斯及其走狗的人比较适合
with greater knowledge of Spartacus and his horde.
某人曾经潜伏在其中
Someone who's lived among them,
对他们的把戏一清二楚
and knows of their treacherous ways.
你这是让我去送死
You would send me to my death.
他们不会对你动手的
They will not lay hand upon you.
我们手里有斯巴达克斯想要的人
We hold something I'm certain Spartacus desires.
要是你错了呢
And if you are in error?
那我就为你哀悼了
Then I shall mourn your passing as well.
这帮混账
Fucking shits.
这都怪我
I hold share of blame.
我急于取悦父亲 才不慎上了钩
I latched upon bait lured with praise and paternal pride.
他肯定知道那些人是斯巴达克斯的人
He must have known they stood Spartacus' men,
伪装而成的
draped in false mantle.
等叫到我们时 不要跟他们打
Do not raise weapon when called upon.
我们宁死也不能成为他们的玩物
We will not give entertainment in our deaths.
记住 我们是罗马人
Remember that we are Romans,
他们只是该死的奴隶
and they nothing but slaves.
可戴着镣铐的是你
Yet you are the one in chains.
是不是觉得很重
A heavy thing, is it not?
因为主人一时性起就宣判你的命运
To be so condemned to the whims of a master?
你从来没有戴过镣铐
You were never placed in chains.
是你亲手给我戴上的
You forged them with your own hands.
将无形的镣铐戴在我心头
Each unseen link binding heart
逼迫我离开你父亲
forcing me from the arms of your father.
帮我逃走 我就让你回到他的身边
See me from these chains, and I shall return you to them.
不管发生了什么事 克芮
His heart yet beats for you, Kore.
他仍然深爱着你
Despite all that has happened.
他还爱着我吗
He still hold love for me?
为了你 他愿意付出一切
And would move the heavens to regain you.
我想都不敢想
I have not dared to hope such a thing.
谢谢
Gratitude.
夜幕降临时我会再来
Know that I shall return at night fall.
看你是怎么死的
When it is your time to die.
我已经渴盼许久了
A thing I long to lay eyes upon.
距离我当角斗士的那会儿已经很久了
It's been a lifetime since I last stood gladiator.
我不想杀人 不想要什么头衔
Title and purpose I never desired.
罗马却逼迫我和许多兄弟这样做
Rome forced such upon me and many of my brothers.
今夜
And this night…
我们以牙还牙
we shall return favor!
让克拉苏之子和他的鹰犬们见识一下
Let us show the son of Crassus and his men
我们在罗马的淫威之下
what we have learned beneath the heel
学到了什么本事
of their mighty Republic.
我们以此
And in such lesson,
用罗马之血
honor the dead
祭奠阵亡将士
with Roman blood!
我很想知道你的感受
I would know what challenge you present.
没有战友 孤身作战
Absent legions to give aid,
就像你们对克雷斯和艾力冈所做的那样
as they did against Crixus and Agron.
开始
Begin!
我是罗马人
I am a Roman!
我他妈的才不会为了取悦你们…
I will not fight for your fucking entertainment
不想打 那就统统杀死
You will fight, or fall where you stand!
既然罗马人没有勇气独自面对我
If a single Roman lacks courage enough to face me…
那就两个一起上
send two to brace nerve!
我从没看过这种比赛
I have never laid eyes upon the games.
让人回想起昔日的荣耀
They are but dim reflection of their glory.
你好像还很向往这种日子
You speak as if heart yearns for such days.
回到镣铐加身的时代吗 才不
To return to shackle and lash, no.
重温脚下的血与沙
To stand upon the sands again…
认清自我
To know a clear purpose
和肩负的使命
of who you are and what must be done…
这才是召唤我们的力量
That is a thing that calls to all of my kind.
我要更多的血
I would have more blood,
来祭奠我的兄弟克雷斯
to honor my brother Crixus
和所有跟随他英勇赴死的兄弟
and all who have followed him to the afterlife!
甘尼克斯
Gannicus!
你来
Take position!
二打一毫无难度可言
Two Romans seem to deliver no contest!
一次来三个 才够祭奠我兄弟
Send three, so that I may deliver proper tribute!
甘尼克斯想要打败你
Gannicus seeks to best you?
角斗士都想击败所有人
Gladiators seek to best all.
只有这样才能在竞技场存活下来
It is the only way to survive in the arena.
在我们这些人里 只有甘尼克斯
Gannicus stands the only among us
在竞技场赢得了自由之身
to win his freedom upon the sands.
既然已经自由了 他干吗还要帮奴隶
If free, why does he raise arms with the slaves
对抗共和国
against the Republic?
他投身起义是为了纪念一位死去的兄弟
He took up cause to honor a fallen brother.
那位兄弟教会了我们如何战斗
One that taught us the ways of battle
以及让所有人团结一心的兄弟情谊
and the bond that joins all men in such pursuit.
你受不了吗
It holds difficulty?
看着你的族人死去
To see one of your people fall?
我早就和他们划清界限了
They no longer stand as such.
我被共和国所抛弃
I have been cast from the Republic,
对于死亡和伤痛已经见怪不怪了
with less thought towards loss or suffering.
我也许会逃避这些血腥场面
I may flinch from gory sight…
但要知道我很享受其中的意义
yet know that I revel in its meaning.
只当你代表一千条罗马狗
Would that you stood a thousand men.
我要亲手了断你 祭奠艾力冈在天之灵
Your deaths by my hand worthy of Agron's memory.
你准备好最后一战了吗
You stand prepared for final contest?
克雷斯曾吹嘘他在竞技场上多么厉害
Crixus once boasted of his prowess as a gladiator,
那是他第一次跟我讲话的时候
in first words he ever broke with me.
我当时说我不喜欢角斗比赛
I said I did not favor the games…
但现在我只求一战
now they are all that I long for.
你确定是他吗
You're certain that's him?
别放松防守
Do not lower guard.
你们在说谁
Who do you speak of?
一个我很想见的人
One I long to greet.
我提的是公平交易
I offer fair trade!
拿提比略的性命来换
Five hundred of your men
你们被克拉苏所俘的五百个人
taken in battle against Crassus for Tiberius' life
住手
Hold!
我会考虑你的条件
I would hear of this
这么说他还活着
He lives then?
那小子
The boy?
或许吧
Perhaps.
暂时还没死
For yet a moment.
你还嫌这卑鄙小人骗你不够惨吗
Tell me you do not fall prey to this viper's tongue?
这个条件不是我开的
The words they form are not my own.
你们别以为我会傻到
Do not think me the fool to greet you
主动跑来找你们
with willful fucking intent.
克拉苏竟然会开出这种条件
Crassus would offer such a bargain?
为了那个该死的臭小子
He would offer Jupiter's throne in return
他连朱庇特的王座都可以给你
for festering disease that sprung from noble loins.
他肯定又设了个套 诱骗我们往里面钻
He but attempts to draw us into another plot turning upon itself.
他设个屁的套
He attempts nothing!
这家伙脑袋一根筋
The man is of singular mind.
我可没有他那么…
One I do not fucking share
五百人
Five hundred?
我知道你很想杀了我
Take my life as I know you desire…
但我死了他们也没命
and end theirs as well.
操他妈的
Fuck the Gods.
你没有辱没艾力冈的威名
You honored Agron well.
希望你也不辱克雷斯的威名
As you shall honor Crixus.
献给你们的
For you!
把剑还给我 奴隶
I would have my sword returned to me, slave.
你说这剑是你的
You claim the sword as your own?
可这手感
The way it fits hand,
不是给女人 就是给小屁孩打造的
I thought it forged for woman or sickly child.
你还当我是小屁孩吗
Do you yet consider me sickly child?
这样打起来才有意思
I find you more than expected.
多谢 我还担心你死得太快
Gratitude. I held worries you would die to quickly.
我要取你狗命
I will have your life…
就像我干掉那该死的高卢人一样
As I took the fucking Gaul's
我现在就把这剑还给你
I would see blade returned to you now.
妮维雅
Naevia!
别急着下手
Take pause.
克拉苏提了个条件
Crassus offers trade!
用他儿子的命 换克雷斯手下五百人的命
His son's life for five hundred captured in battle with Crixus!
干掉他
Let her finish him!
不过是罗马狗的谎言
Another Roman lie!
我相信不是谎言
I do not believe it so.
不过我把选择权交给受这小子伤害最深的人
Yet I lay choice with the one most wronged by the boy.
你的性命在我手中
I held your life in my hands.
我要你活着的每一刻都知道 总有一天
Live each moment knowing that one day soon
我会取你狗命
I shall reclaim it.
你就不担心上当吗
Are yet feel come skin conceiving bitter end?
克拉苏不会拿他儿子的命冒险
Crassus will not risk in cost of one he loves.
当初我们也是这样想葛雷博和他妻子的
We thought the same upon Glaber towards his wife.
有信了 我们有几百个人
We have received words. Hundreds of our people
正往约定的人质交换地点前进
march towards where agreed upon to exchange Roman soldiers.
把提比略带过去
Take Tiberius to there.
保证那小子的生命安全
Seize the boy's life so set upon.
杀了他 杀了他
Kill them! Fucking kill him!
你要的人我已经带到了
Delivered into hands, as agreed upon.
我有话跟他说
I would break words.
他离开温暖的怀抱太久了
He has been too long from embrace.
看到你还活着 真让人振奋
It lifts heart. To see you yet of this world.
少跟我油嘴滑舌
Do not ply me with silver tongue.
你知道那些庞培的人是斯巴达克斯的人假扮的
You knew them to be Spartacus' men, under guise of Pompey's.
你这话好大胆
A bold claim.
我父亲肯定会听进我的话
Well one my father will surely take interest in.
送你回他身边的旅程可是危险重重
The journey to return you to his arms is fraught with peril.
尤其对于你这种不教训不知道天高地厚的小子
For one needing to be taught severest lesson in who towers above you.
不
No!
你这个疯婊子 知道你做了什么吗
You mad bitch. Do you know what you have done?
我只是讨回公道
I have balanced fucking scale.
我们五百个兄弟都将因此受难
Five hundred of our people will suffer for this.
现在这小子毫无价值
The boy holds no value now.
恺撒也一样
Nor does life of Caesar.
等等 克拉苏会如约交易的
Wait! Crassus will yet honor trade!
只要他得到另一样他所渴望的东西
If you give him something else his heart desires.
是一个叛贼杀了他
He was struck down by hand of rebel slave,
就在我们从斯巴达克斯的营地撤出来的时候
as we attempted to withdraw from Spartacus' camp.
那人上了年纪 主人给他刻的标记
A man long of years, the scars of his master
深深地烙进了肉里
etched deep upon flesh.
那你还履行了交易
And yet you held to fucking bargain?
我知道你必然伤痛欲绝
I knew wound such loss would cause.
当发现有机会抚平你的伤痛 我便出手了
I sought only to balm it with opportunity presented…
谢谢 盖乌斯
Gratitude, Gaius.
你现在代我行使权力
You now stand my Word and my Will.
受你重托
You honor me.
准备行军
Prepare the men for march.
我要大举进攻斯巴达克斯
I would press towards Spartacus
要他死无葬身之地
and see him to deserved end.
遵命
Imperator.
看着我
Raise eyes.
马科斯
Marcus
从今以后
From this day forth…
你要认清我主人的身份
you shall address me as Dominus.
真希望我们的爱人也在人群当中
Would that those we held to heart stood among them.
纳西尔
Nasir…
诸神把你送回我怀里
The gods return you to my arms.
离开你是我太傻了
I was fool to ever leave them.
今晚 我们与本以为再也见不到的
This night hearts lift in joyous reunion
兄弟相会 这是大喜事
with those thought lost to us.
父亲们
Fathers.
兄弟姐妹们
Brothers and sisters.
儿子与爱人
Sons and lovers.
在罗马阴影的笼罩下 我们紧紧相拥
Hold them close for the shadow of Rome is upon us.
我们今后同呼吸共命运
We shall seek our destiny together.
无论代价如何
Whatever the cost.
我们永远不要忘记
Yet let us not pass from memory
那些离开了我们的兄弟
those left absent from our arms.
那些牺牲他们的生命
Those who sacrificed their lives
换来我们自由生活的人
so that all may live free.
克雷斯
For Crixus!
苏拉
For Sura.
维罗和米拉
For Varro and Mira!
奥诺玛默斯
For Oenomaus!
迪欧特莫斯
For Diotimus!
莱斯克斯
For Rhaskos.
赛纳斯
For Sanus!
多纳
Donar!
杜罗
For Duro!
阿卡
For Aca.
佛蒂斯
Fortis!
巴尔卡
Barca!
纳美特斯
Nemetes!
李斯卡斯
Liscus!
克雷斯 克雷斯
For Crixus! Crixus! Crixus…
Crixus! Crixus!
克雷斯 克雷斯
让他的名字回荡天际 刺破苍穹
Split heavens with the sound of his name!
要克拉苏和庞培知道
Let it carry to Crassus and Pompey
这洪钟雷鸣 是腥风血雨的前奏
as distant thunder promising storm and blood!
我们尚能一战的兄弟将向罗马发起最后一击
All those who are able shall make final stand against Rome.
我在此发誓
And this I promise you.
我们要么自由生活
We will live free…
要么与兄弟黄泉相见
or join our brothers in death!